<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proposals, and reasons whereon some of them are grounded, humbly presented to the Parliament, towards the settling of a religious and godly government in the commonwealth with a short account of the compatibility of the congregationall way with the magistrates ordering all matters of religion in a nationall publick way ..., tythes and settled maintenance for the ministery, [and] ministers capacity of sitting in Parliament / by Lewis du Moulin ...</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Lewis, 1606-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36843</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142140</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97969</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264196351</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14089</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13142140</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 415:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proposals, and reasons whereon some of them are grounded, humbly presented to the Parliament, towards the settling of a religious and godly government in the commonwealth with a short account of the compatibility of the congregationall way with the magistrates ordering all matters of religion in a nationall publick way ..., tythes and settled maintenance for the ministery, [and] ministers capacity of sitting in Parliament / by Lewis du Moulin ...</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Lewis, 1606-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Redmayne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97969:1"/>
            <p>PROPOSALS AND REASONS Whereon some of them are grounded: Humbly presented to the PARLIAMENT Towards the settling of a Religious and Godly Government in the Commonwealth: With a short account, <hi>Of</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>the compatibility of the Congregationall way with the Magistrates or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all matters of Religion in a Nationall publick way: and of the Incompatibility of either of them, with an Ecclesiasticall Presbyterian-National, Iurisdiction, Independent on the Magistrat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tythes and settled maintenance for the Ministery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ministers capacity of sitting in Parliament.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By LEWIS du MOULIN, Professour of History in the University of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN REDMAYNE, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposals">
            <pb facs="tcp:97969:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97969:2"/>
            <head>PROPOSALS, Towards the settling of a Religious &amp; Godly Government in the Commonwealth.</head>
            <div n="1" type="proposal">
               <head>1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Commonwealth be consisting of one entire represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative called Parliament, made up of three other representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> one representative for each Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposal">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>That 340 be the representative of England, 40 the representative for Scotland, and 20 the representative for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposal">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>That England and Scotland bear the burden of taxes and imposi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions according to the number of men in their representative.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposal">
               <head>4.</head>
               <p>That the number of Members, for Shires, Cities and Burroughs be proportionable to the rates of taxes and their contribution, that Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall have lesse members, and London a far greater number, that cities and Burroughs have but one, and Shires more then two.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposal">
               <head>5.</head>
               <p>That men of all rankes that have a competency of estate be chosen by their Countrey, and that Ministers of the Gospell be made capable of being elected and of sitting and voting in Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposal">
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>That the Parliament sit at Westminster every year, 3 months to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="proposal">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97969:3"/>
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>That in the first Parliament, all the 400 out of the three representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives be chosen and sent at once.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="proposal">
               <head>8.</head>
               <p>That it be provided for in the succession of ensuing Parliaments, that one 100 of these 400 go off, &amp; other 100 be sent in their room, who are to be elected not by the three Nations, but by the fourth part of each Nation, so that no man or Country be put upon election of members, but once in 4 years,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="proposal">
               <head>9.</head>
               <p>That the first sitting Parliament doe chuse 40 of their own body to be a standing perpetuall Council of State, whereof 10 to go off eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year, and 10 others be suppylyed by the Parliament of that year.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="proposal">
               <head>10.</head>
               <p>That of those 10 that are to go off, some or most or all of them may be chosen again that same year by the Parliament if they please.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="proposal">
               <head>11.</head>
               <p>That the Parliament or the Councill of State chuse a President of the Councill, who in the Intervalls of Parliaments may receive some stamp of authority, (as a Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi>) only in publike meetings out of the sitting of the Councill, which will be a badge of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths Majesty attending him, although he hath but a single vote in the Councill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="proposal">
               <head>12.</head>
               <p>That this Councill have power in the Intervalls of Parliament to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse all grievances, order all matters, which other courts do not; make ordinances, but no Acts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="proposal">
               <head>13.</head>
               <p>That all Ecclesiasticall Iurisdiction be abolished &amp; be buried with the English Episcopal Hierarchy, and that the Parliament and the Councill of State under them be invested with a supreme Iurisdiction in all causes and matters, and over all persons, suffering no collaterality of jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions within the Commonwealth, in Nationall assemblies by what title soever distinguished; and that all Acts of jurisdiction, as ordination, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position and excommunication (if any be admitted) be a product of the Commons-wealths jurisdiction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="proposal">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97969:3"/>
               <head>14.</head>
               <p>That the Ministers of the Gospell may be as well chōsen members of the Councill of State as of the Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="proposal">
               <head>15.</head>
               <p>That no religion be commanded by law, and no man constrained to repair to ordinances; yet that all men be invited and encouraged to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them, and no religion tolerated, but that which agreeth with the confessions of Faith of the late re. Assembly of Divines (the 30 and 31 chapters only excepted) or with that of the Reverend Ministers of the congregational way, who met in the year 1658. in the house called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="proposal">
               <head>16.</head>
               <p>That for a constant succession and supply of Ministers, ten men of the Councill of State, and a competent number of Godly and learned Ministers, holding to the forenamed confessions of Faith make up a Committee for visiting the Universiries, Schools of learning, naming a Vichancellour, conferring or bestowing of Halls, receiving appeals from judgements given in the Universities, and for examining, trying and approving of fit men for Parish-Churches, and investing of such as are duely presented by the Patron, or chosen by particular Parish-Churches, or are demanded for lecturers, and have a good testimony of their life and doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="proposal">
               <head>17.</head>
               <p>The Parochial and congregationall Ministers may severally or asun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, meet by the leave of the said committee, or Councill of State, in their respective Countreys or Shires in the form of Synodes or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall assemblies, to give advise to Ministers or Churches, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate matters of Religion, but not to impose their declarations upon neighbour Ministers or Churches, except they receive the stamp of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick authority from the Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="proposal">
               <head>18.</head>
               <p>That in Scotland, Ireland, and parts remote from London, some sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>committees delegated from the Higher committee be settled of the same nature and to the same intent and purpose.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="proposal">
               <head>19.</head>
               <p>That the Ministers that are for the Congregational way, as they are indifferently to be invested with Parochiall livings with others of a different judgement, so they must be exhorted not to attend their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97969:4"/>private congregations, at those times when the Parochial assemblies do meet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="proposal">
               <head>20.</head>
               <p>That not only Tythes be reserved for the maintenance of Parochial Ministers, but that some larger allowance be provided for more Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, specially in such large Parishes as that of Sepulcher, Cripple-gate, Giles and Martin in the fields, &amp;c. to attend the Pastorall Parochial du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as Catechising, visiting the sick and prisoners, conforting the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, instructing the ignorant, admonishing privately the carelesse and the unruly, and taking notice of the poor and needy, that their wants be represented: and that for augmentation of maintenance some way be found to make a stock of mony, towards the buying of impropriations, not only for Ministers, but also for increase of revenue to Colledges and Schools, and erecting new ones; furnishing of Parish-Churches with Libraries, and supplying the wants of the poor, the widdow and the fatherlesse</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="proposal">
               <head>21.</head>
               <p>That the Parliament be pleased to mind the propagation of the Gospell, not only in the three Nations, but also abroad, settling revenues towards the maintenance of strangers, Students in Divinity for remote Countreys, as <hi>Poland, Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. that have no means nor Schools, where to bring up Schollars, and fit them for the Ministery, being no lesse zealous for the truth, then Popish Magistrates for their Idolatrous superstition, while they carefully nurture youth in their Seminaries for England and other Countreys.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="proposal">
               <head>22.</head>
               <p>That the names of Presbyterians and Independants be quite abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, and that the Parliament do allow and countenance, as well the Ministers of the congregational way, as others in their Parochial meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, countenancing the congregational way for those that are grown up Christians, so as that in the mean while he do settle a National Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for Christians of all sizes and growth; particularly for the main body of the people of the Land. Which, were there no other Church way but the congregational, would remain carelesse and ignorant of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97969:4"/>
            <head>REASONS, Whereon Some of the Proposals are grounded.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPT. 1. <hi>Of the compatibility of the Congregationall way with the Magistrates ordering all matters of Religion in a Nationall publick way; and of the incompatibility of either of them with an Ecclesiasticall Presbyterian Nationall Iurisdiction, Independent on the Magistrat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ventured upon some Proposals towards the settling of a Commonwealth, in order to a Religious and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government, the only way to preserve it; I will forbear to give Reasons for the same in this Modell, except it be only for the three heads mentioned in the title-page.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now in this Chapter I purpose to assert in brief,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Souverain Magistrat of each dominion and territory, is entrusted by God to have the sole principall and chief power to order matters of Religion in a Nationall church way, and consequently that the Ministers of the Gospell are not invested with any jurisdiction to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and settle in a publick way the matters of Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Churches of the congregationall way are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible with the Magistrates power in ordering a nationall church way. From these two assertions it will be inferred, that an Ecclesiasticall Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall Classicall Iurisdiction, excommunicating, deposing and making lawes, independently on the Magistrate, is contrary to Scripture and reason, and is incompatible both with the Magistrates jurisdiction and the Congregationall way.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>For the proof of the first assertion, I will bring arguments and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, not following any accurat order.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97969:5"/> 1. By the nature of obedience. As the holy Scripture doth propound but two great ordinances, the Ministery and Magistracy, by which men are governed in this world, and led into the possession of the next; so nature, reason and custume, yea and the practise of all Nations doe meet in this Scripture truth, that there are but two waies, whereby men do submit themselves and obey their commands, orders, advises and counsels; the one when the inward men, that is, the intellect, the will, the heart, the affections and the conscience are drawn, led, convicted and perswaded; the other when the outward man is constrained to obey for fear of punishment, by the one of these waies, the Magistrat doth build his Empire and dominion: And by the other way Iesus Christ buildeth his Kingdome, converting mens souls to faith and repentance by the Ministery of the Gospell. Men yield to the jurisdiction of the Magistrat both for conscience sake and for fear of constraint and force by punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but they submit to the jurisdiction of Ministers only for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science sake, and because they are perswaded to submit themselves to it: the commandments of the one afford not the liberty to interpret them, but impose an obligation of submission with a blind judgement, whereas the lawes and orders of the Ministers give that liberty which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave to the people of <hi>Berea,</hi> who did no further obey his predication, then they found it agreable to other Scriptures, and were convinced and perswaded of the truth of his Doctrine. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us but these two waies of submission in the 13. chapter of the Epistle to the Romans, either that way which we take meerely for conscience sake, or over and above for fear of wrath, that is for fear of outward pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment: let the Magistrat be what he will, Christian or heathen, let him be orthodox or heretick, there is but one of these two waies of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to him. In short, we obey and submit to the exhortations of wise men, because we apprehend them by a judgement of discretion and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation to be wholesome and usefull, and for fear lest the neglect of them prove a sin against God, and be dangerous to our present or our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall condition, &amp; not for fear of wrath from any censure of men; such are the exhortations of Ministers to faith &amp; repentance, yea their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as when they bid us be reconciled to God, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands carry along with them an indispensable obligation in the court of conscience; but though they have power and authority of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, they have no power to constrain those that will not yield to their commands, no more then those of the Physitians.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97969:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p n="2">II. By the nature of the power and authority called the power of the keyes, and binding and loosing. This power is the same that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Doctors had under the Old Testament in the Synagogues &amp; houses of prayers; a power not forcing the body, but enlightening the mind, convincing the heart, ruling the affections, and bringing them captive to the obedience of the crosse; a power which the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mentioned in an hundred places, and yet is never taken for a Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall Presbyterian power of deposing, excommunicating, &amp; making lawes and canons authoritatively; but alwaies for the vertue and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the spirit of God in the word and ministery called the power of God, Rom. 1. v. 16. by which men are turned from darknesse to light, from the Kingdome of Satan to God, Act. 26. v. 18. a power described in magnificent termes, 2. Cor. 10. v. 6. a power which S. <hi>Austin. Ep.</hi> 48. <hi>ad Vincentium,</hi> opposeth to the power of the Magistrate, <hi>Pastoris est per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducere ad veritatem persuadendo, Magistratus cogendo,</hi> by this power the Ministers are Ambassadors from the Kingdome of Christ to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world, where they are to deliver their Maisters message; but, as Ambassadors, so Ministers are barely to denounce their Maisters will, beseeching those they are sent to, yea commanding them in the name of their Maister to be reconciled to God without putting any force upon them, except it be by that weapon which no man can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand Act. 6. v. 16. I know no other power of the keyes nor of binding and loosing: though probably this power of the keyes may carry some thing more, which was particularly given to the Apostles, as learned Mr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> tells us in his Harmony Matth. 16. He saith that the power of binding and loosing was only given to the Apostles as far as some part of Moses law was to stand in practise, and some to be laid aside; some things under the law prohibited were now to be permitted, and some things permitted to be now prohibited: so that in these words <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever,</hi> &amp;c. Christ promiseth to the Apostles such an assistance of his spirit and giveth them such a power, that what they allowed to stand in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise should stand and what to fall, should fall; in short what they bound in earth should be bound in heaven: and this exposition is the more agreable, because the Greek Text speaks not of binding or loosing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons but things, saying not, whomsoever you shall bind, but whatsoever things ye shall bind, &amp;c. that is whatsoever things ye shall dispense or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97969:6"/>unto. He also parallels this place of binding and loosing to Iohn 20. v. 22. <hi>whose sins ye retain they are retained,</hi> &amp;c. and saith that that power was a particular gift to the Apostles, when Christ breathed on them, by which they spoke strange tongues, healed diseases, killed and made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, delivered to Satan and bestowed the holy Ghost, or the power to work the same miracles, whatever exposition of these we receive, none suites with the power of excommunicating and ruling by a judiciall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§. 3.</head>
                  <p n="3">III. By the nature of ordination, which was alwaies in England as it ought to be an Act of the Magistrates jurisdiction: by ordination I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, a licence or a priviledge granted by a power of Magistracy to a man to use that ministeriall function which God hath called him unto, and to be acknowledged a Minister of the Gospell in all the places of his jurisdiction; for all the Acts of the Magistrate, of the Church and of the Ministers, are not to send him, but to acknowledge Gods call and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and publickly to declare their willingnesse and readinesse to accept of his ministery among them. If there were a call from men, it should be rather from the particular church electing of him for their Pastor, and requiring his pains among them: all other acts arising from the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of his life and doctrine and the begging of God blessing by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters met in a <hi>coetus</hi> presbyterie or Synod by prayer and fasting, the giving the hand of fellowship, the laying on the hands, are acts necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be supposed before a man be acknowledged Minister of the Gospell and set a part by God for the great work of saving souls. The Ministers doth no more concurr in making or sending a Minister then in marrying; whereas, it is God that instituted and made matrimony, and the mutuall consent of the man and woman made them husband and wife; the Ministers begge only a blessing upon their marriage: and here the Magistrate by his license contributes to their marriage as much as he doth to the making of a Minister: all the <hi>Ius Divinum</hi> of the call, is Gods call concurring with the choice made by men or by a particular church; whereof we find an evident example in Ezechiel 33. where God declareth by his Prophet that whatever watchman the people should chuse, he would repute the choice to be his act, in that he would punish those that should sleight the admonitions of the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and did not take them for Gods warnings; and would take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97969:6"/>of the watchman for his failing in the care of mens souls, in which example we may see that there is much labour lost in asserting the <hi>Ius Divinum</hi> of the Ministery, as if it had nothing of humane right; for if Magistrate and people doe chuse themselves a watchman over their own souls to divide the word unto them, why should not this act be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a Divine choice and a Divine installing into the calling, as well as the choice of the watchman, whereof mention is made in Ezechiel? I conceive that this is the true notion of Ministers ordination, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by all Lutheran Churches, namely by <hi>Gerardus</hi> in his common places <hi>de Minist. Ecclesias §.</hi> 12. and <hi>Chytraeus in cap.</hi> 25. <hi>Exodi;</hi> both hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ordination, is nothing else, but a publick acknowledgement of the mission and call that God hath made of such a man, and a begging the blessing of God upon his Ministery, and upon the choice that the Church hath made of him. <hi>Iohn Mestrezat</hi> of Paris in his tract of the Church is of the same opinion and so <hi>Daniel Tilenus</hi> part. 2. disp. 25. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors in the ordination have nothing to do, but to acknowledge Gods call and their liking of it.</hi> But the ordination of Priests in the Iewish Church sheweth, that it was not a product or an act of the jurisdiction of the Priests, whose urisdiction (if they had any) was confounded with that of the Magistrate: for we shall see next that as Priests they never had any. Ordination then being no act of the Ministers, much lesse of their juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, it is consequently evident that deposition or exauctoration is no act of the Ministers jurisdiction: for it is but raveling again what was done without any intervening jurisdiction but that of the Magistrate, who withdraweth his license; the Ministers say they will hold him no longer a fellow partner in the work of the Gospel; the people declare their dislike of the man and professe they will make no use further of his Ministery; which act is no otherwise an act of jurisdiction, then the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to take physick is an act of the patients jurisdiction over the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian; much like the excommunicating of a man by Ministers and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which is no otherwise an act of jurisdiction then their withdrawing from his communion; and indeed excommunication is an act of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall and ministeriall jurisdiction of the same stamp with ordination and deposition, and they all rise and fall together, and therefore it will not be requisite I should show the nullity and vanity of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and professe my dissent from the reverend Ministers of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, who hold in their reasons given to the dissenting brethren, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97969:7"/>is as well an ordinance of Christ as preaching and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration of the Sacraments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p n="4">IV. By the nature of the sacred function, which by Gods institution was never attended with jurisdiction, this is made evident by what we have said of the power of binding and loosing, and by the example of those that were clothed with that sacred function; for they never exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised any jurisdiction by vertue of their function; for the high Priest as <hi>Maimonides</hi> tells us was not alwaies admitted a member of the great Sanedrim, and sure he could never have missed to be one of them, if his function had carried along with it a jurisdiction, as the office of a Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour or Lord keeper requireth that the man that hath it should sit in a Parliament. And <hi>Simon Iannes,</hi> &amp;c. who invaded the Kingdom ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought by their Priesthood to have more right to the Soverain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, besides, that the very installing into that office was no act of Priestly jurisdiction, but of the Sanedrim or of the King; and the Priests were so unprovided of jurisdiction, that when Kings or Iudges were removed, the people lived as they listed, and were left loose as sheep without a shepheard and as a great family of servants without a head. Aaron for all his Priestly office in chief was not able to restrain the people from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; yea he was rather their servant in the absence of Moses, and put by them to make a golden calf. The very papists when they have been in a good mood, have been pleased to acknowledge this truth, when they have had occasion to clip the wings of the Pope; but especially the words of the canon law are expresse, <hi>can. inter</hi> 33. <hi>qu.</hi> 3. <hi>what the Priest cannot compasse by the word of his Doctrine, the supreme power must needs do by the ter rour of discipline: by such means the celestiall Kingdom is assisted by the earthly Kingdom, for, the holy Church hath no other sword then the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, which hath a quickening power.</hi> And <hi>Anselm.</hi> Arch Bishop of Canterbury upon the 16. of Matthew proves at large, that the Priest hath no weapon but a spirituall one, constraining those that are willing to have force put upon them; but of the material sword in the hand of the Magistrate, he saith, that it constrains even those that are unwilling to be constrained, Hotoman a civil Lawyer takes off all jurisdiction from the ministeriall function in his book of the liberties of the Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane Church: he hath these words, <hi>is is certain that Ecclesiasticks as Ecclesiasticks have neither fisck nor territory, nor any jurisdiction, but only
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97969:7"/>liberty to declare what is fitting to be observed without being able to put their opinion in execution.</hi> Among Protestatns <hi>Salmasius</hi> a man of more credit in this, because he spoke against the sence of those Pastors whose congregations he resorted, in his <hi>Apparatus</hi> p. 158. <hi>among all the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Ministers there is not one that can be named, in the discharge of which any jurisdiction is requisite; there needs none for instructing the faithfull people, nor for the administration of the Sacraments:</hi> he further saith, that what ever jurisdiction they can challenge it is over those that willingly submit to it; <hi>for an impenitent person and one that little cares for their censure doth not belong to the Ministers jurisdiction and care: In administring the holy Supper there is no jurisdiction since it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to those only that are willing to take it,</hi> so that all excommunication must be void, except it light upon one that is willing to be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p n="5">V. By the example of the State of the Nation of Iewes, where. 1. the jurisdiction of the Church was united with that of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as almost all the Romanists acknowledge, namely <hi>Baronius, Carthusianus, Cornel.</hi> a <hi>Lapide, Tostatus,</hi> &amp;c. the words of <hi>Tostatus</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expresse upon the 16. of Matthew, <hi>under the Old Testament it was not necessary that jurisdictions should be distinct, by reason it was but one nation, one people, one temple; and because they might easily be governed by an unity of jurisdictions to the end that God might be thought one and the same God to whom they all ministred.</hi> There being but one jurisdiction, there could not be an Ecclesiasticall, Nationall jurisdiction in dependent on the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates jurisdiction, and therefore all the Churches censures, deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, excommunication (if they had any) were but products of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates jurisdiction: most of the Protestants goe along with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists for an identity of jurisdictions, whereupon it will not be amisse to hear judicious R. <hi>Hooker</hi> in the 8. book of his Ecclesiasticall policy, when he maintains that the Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction in England, as being not distinct from that of the King, is agreeable to the government of the people of God, these be his words, <hi>Our State is according to the pattern of Gods own ancient elect people, which people was not part of them the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and part of them the Church of God, but the self same people, whole and entire, were both under one chief Governor, on whose supreme authority they did all depend.</hi> So also is Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> for an identity of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97969:8"/>jurisdiction among the Iewes in the 9. chapter of his book touching the Government of the Church, he saith, <hi>The Sanedrim consisted of the chief of that people, as well as of the Priests and Levites, because the chief causes of that Commonwealth as well as of religion passed through their hands.</hi> Now if in a Nation rude and weak in knowledge under a burdensome administration, loaden with ceremonies and legall rites, where the sixt part of the people was either judge, leader, elder, Priest, Prophet, Levite or officer in the Leviticall service. If I say under such an administration where there was need of many keepers, guardians, tutors, many helps of government, yet the government was not shared betwixt the keepers of Ecclesiasticall and the keepers of civill jurisdiction, but one only ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction was over all persons and regulated all matters; how much lesse need is there to make two jurisdictions collaterall in one and the same people among Christians, wholly freed from that burdensome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration of lawes and officers: for if, when the faithfull had need of many pedagogues and schoolmaisters, yet they were governed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out distinction of jurisdiction of Church and State, much lesse do Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians now need such a distinct government, since they are wholly freed from the necessity of having so many guides and masters to govern and teach them so many rudiments, and to acquaint them with the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the ceremonies? besides, there is lesse need of a distinct govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the State from that of the Church, whereof God never gave any platform under the New Testament; and what need an Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call jurisdiction, where there is no Ecclesiasticall law or constitution? but admit there had been among the lewes an Ecclesiasticall jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on distinct from the civill, and that the Priests and Levites had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested with the Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction, yet no jurisdiction would thence accrue to the Ministers of the Gospell, who have not succeeded to the Priests and Levites, which mainly attended the ceremonial wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, but to the Prophets, the Rabbies and Doctors, who were wholly conversant about the doctrinal worship, and taught in schools and houses of prayers, and who never had a share in the jurisdiction, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly over the inward man; 'tis true, Samuel taught in such schools and yet was a Iudge of the Land, but this was an extraordinary case and his soverain jurisdiction was not inherent in his Propheticall office or Ministery of teaching his schollars the young Prophers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the Commonwealth of Israel the King and Soverain Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97969:8"/>had the main ordering of all matters of religion; and this the story of the Kings and the Chronicles show all along. Now if the good Kings of Iuda exercised that power, (as none will I believe question,) in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God and to a spirituall end, I do not understand why a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magistrates power, duty &amp; end should not be of the like extent: shall not these be alike obliged to fear God, to read the Scripture, to ordain lawes for reforming religion, extirpating Idolatry, blasphemy and all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and false worship, appoint orthodox and godly Pastors? <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus</hi> de <hi>Marca</hi> a Papist, a great schollar, and very learned in Divinity, though not a Priest or Bishop or a divine as they term it, in his book, <hi>de concordia Imperii &amp; sacerdotii lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. saith, <hi>that it is a great wrong done to Christian Princes to deny them the same measure that the Kings of Iuda had. Insignts injuria fit Principibus Christianis si eam in Ecclesia potestatem illis denegamus quam Reges Iudaeorum in Synagoga obtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p n="6">VI. By the example of the Christian Emperours, Constantine the great, Theodosius, Iustinian, &amp;c. who modelled the Nationall Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way after the civill government, set up Episcopal courts and Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Iudicatures depending on them; convocated synods, gave the vigor of lawes to their canons and determinations, and made lawes and constitutions of times without the consent of their clergy, for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and regulating all church matters, whether of faith or of disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, appointed Ecclesiasticall censures, and set bonds to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and many times made them void and null, by their single autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p n="7">VII. By the very confession of the Nationall Presbyterian Church of Scotland art. 25. <hi>To Kings, Princes, rulers and Magistrates chiefly and most principally the conservation and the purgation of religîon pertaineth, so that, not only they are appointed for civil policy, but also for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the true Religion and for suppressing Idolatry and all superstition whatsoever.</hi> He who hath never heard of a Nationall Presbyterian ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction independent on the Magistrat, or of a double jurisdiction Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall and civil, would not deduct it by any consequence out of the words of this confession: for, they make the Magistrat sole Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Churches and assemblies nationall, provinciall, classicall, &amp;c.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97969:9"/>and judge of heresies, canons, decrees and church censures, and they doe equally lay upon him the duty of extirpating heresies, reforming the church and purging the Commonwealth from seditions, abuses, crimes, &amp;c. yea the word <hi>principally</hi> puts more stress of duty upon the Magistrate, to govern the Church and maintain and reverence the true religion; then to rule the Commonwealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p n="8">VIII. By the lawes of England never yet repealed since the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: they unite all Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction to the Crown, even that jurisdiction which visiteth, reformeth, correcteth and rectifieth all abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, heresies, enormities whatsoever, and so the Statute Elizab. 1 forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that any tenet should be delivered and passe currant for heresie, which was not first declared to be heresie by the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>§. 9.</head>
                  <p n="9">IX. By the sence and Declaration of this present Parliament in their publick Commission, by which they called the Assembly of Divines: for the Assembly was bound thereby <hi>not to exercise any jurisdiction and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Ecclesiasticall whatsoever, or any other power; but to advise and give counsell concerning such things as shall be propounded to them, and to deliver their opinions and advices.</hi> And the same they manifested by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise; for, having perfected the confession of faith, Catechisme and plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of government, they did not impose them upon the people of the Land, as a Law and decree of their own, and as a product of their Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction, but presented them to the Parliament under the name of <hi>Humble Advice,</hi> albeit they make use of another language, <hi>pro Imperio</hi> in the same confession, when they say chapt. 31. sect. 3. <hi>that Ministers in Synods may determine Authoritatively.</hi> But this power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated to the Assembly and the exercise of the same &amp; granted while they sate at Westminster, is a true representation of the extent of power, which all Synods and Councils under an orthodox Magistrate ever er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed or ought to have, for without a power of Magistracy giving force of law to their determinations and decrees, they are meerly advices and counsels, and were they so many Apostles met in Counsell, they could but say as Act. 15.29. <hi>If you keep our decrees you shall doe well.</hi> And certainly had the Lord Iesus Christ instituted a jurisdiction distinct, as they say, from the civil Magistrate, they ought to have disclaimed that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97969:9"/>ordinance of Parliament which delegated a power which was none of their own, and straitned it too; for, what commission needed they from men, if they had a jurisdiction immediately from Christ? they were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have expected an ordinance directed, not to the Ministers, but to the people, who should have been enjoined to suffer the Ministers to exercise that jurisdiction, which they authoritatively challenge from Iesus Christ and to receive the Assemblies conclusions, not as humble advices but as Ecclesiasticall lawes and ordinances, made authoritative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Governors of the Churches under Iesus Christ.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 10.</head>
                  <p n="10">X. By the testimony of the re. Ministers of the congregational way, namely of Mr. <hi>Ieremiah Burroughs,</hi> who in his <hi>Irenicum</hi> professeth to deliver nothing but the judgement of his brethren, all dissenting as well as he from the brethren of the Presbytery, pag. 21. he saith, that Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates are specially to aime at the promoting of the Kingdom of Iesus Christ: and there throughout the long chapter he hath these conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, 1. that the power of the Magistrate is alike in the times of the old, and of the New Testament; that it was not only a law given to the Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, but known by the heathen, by the light of nature, that Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was to govern and order religion as well as other things. 2. That there was no distinction of jurisdictions in the Commonwealth of Israel. 3. That it is most unreasonable that a Magistrate turning either from the heathenish or Iewish religion, should enjoy lesse power in matter of religion, then he had when he was either a heathen or a Iew. <hi>An infidel Magistrate,</hi> saith he, <hi>converted to Christian Religion is thereby better ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to perform the duty of his place then before, but he had the same autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity before.</hi> 4. He holds, that a Magistrate hath a soverain judgement of his commands, though unskilfull in the things commanded. <hi>A Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, that is not skilfull in physick or in navigation, yet he may judge Physitians and Mariners, if they wrong others in their way.</hi> 5. He asserts largely the power of Magistracy in matters of religion by the example of the Kings of Iuda and Israel, yea of the Kings of Niniveh and of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes interposing his power in matters of religion, for which Ezra blessed God, <hi>whosoever will not doe the law of thy God and the law of the King let judgement be executed upon him.</hi> Hereupon he presseth many passages of Scripture, Isa. 49.22, 23. <hi>Kings shall be thy nursing fathers,</hi> and Revel. 21. v. 24. Rom. 13.4. 1. Pet. 2.13. He addes also that, <hi>since the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97969:10"/>Scripture speaks thus generally for thy good, for the punishment of evil doers and the praise of them that doe well we must not distinguish where the Scripture doth not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 11.</head>
                  <p n="11">XI. By the confession of many Romish writers constrained by the evidence of the truth. The canon law saith out of <hi>Isidorus, causa</hi> 23. <hi>qu.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>let secular Princes know they ought to give an account of the Church, which God hath committed to their trust, and whether the disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church be made better or worse they are to give an account of it to God, who submitted the Church to their jurisdiction.</hi> Now who would think, that the Magistrate should be found to give an account of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others mans administration and charge? <hi>Claude Fauchet</hi> a famous Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian a Papist in his book of the liberties of the Gallican Church, out of Gregory of Tours, and the practise of his time, proveth that the Kings of France were reputed heads of the Church, a title which many 100. yeares after was much found fault with in the Kings of England by the Romanists, yea also by some reformers; he concludes his discourse thus, <hi>that the Bishops of that time did hold the King assisted by his Councill of State to be under God, head on earth of the Church in his Kingdom and not the Pope; whom if they had looked on as the head, they would have sent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the conclusion of the councell of Orleans and not to King Clovis.</hi> In latter times then this Clovis even in the dayes of Lewis the 9. who was sainted by the Pope, I find in a writter named Ionville, of above 400. yeares standing, chapter 82. a notable example in the darkest times of popery of the nullity and vanity of Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction, unlesse it were set a work by some power of Magistracy; shewing that Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall jurisdiction and excommunication are like the feathers of an arrow, which can never hit nor have a direct motion without the wood put to it. When a Prelat had desired of King Lewis the help of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular power for making his excommunications good, the King an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, <hi>that with all his heart he would do it, but that first it was fit he should be acquainted with the validity of excommunication.</hi> I will not omit the Author of the Councill of Trent a learned popish writer, and worthy that Dr. Langban, late Provost of Queen Colledge in Oxford should turn it into English, he every where devests all church-men of jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. In the 6. book chap. 5. <hi>The Ecclesiasticks in France doe not hold their Ecclesiastick jurisdiction from the Pope but from the King, though the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97969:10"/>Iesuites teach otherwise.</hi> and in the 7. book ch. 7. he ascribeth a function to Pastors, but no jurisdiction, he hath this passage worthy to be written in golden letters, for, it doth disannull and make void all these Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall, classicall, synodicall canons, sentences and determinations, which are not acts of the Magistrate; <hi>Kings,</hi> saith he, <hi>ought not to meddle with the administration of the Sacraments, nor with the businesse of ceremonies, or other Ecclesiasticall or ministeriall Acts: but as for appointing the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ceremonies, purging out of abuses, extirpation of schismes and heresies, Church policy and the like, they may, they ought, and they have alwayes done it, either by putting their own hands to the work, or by commanding it, or else by appointing and constituting lawes, statutes, and ordinances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By what hath been said hitherto, it is evident that in the same territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and nation a nationall Church way cannot be compatible with the Nationall jurisdiction of the Magistrate, whereof a platform was endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be settled in Scotland, when they gave us a supreme judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in their generall assembly over all the Churches of Scotland, and another judicatory in the Parliament over the Republick or civill Estate of Scotland, for if all the Acts, as we have seen of the pretended Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall jurisdiction, as ordination, deposition, and excommunication, are acts of the same nature, with such as are brought forth by a power of Magistracy, it is not possible to conceive two coordinate collateral na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional jurisdictions within the same Nation and territory over the same persons, conversant about the same lawes and ordinances, and the same matter of religion. I conclude with the words of Musculus <hi>loc. com. de Magistratibus. The way and nature of Government cannot bear that in the same people, there be two authentick powers, two diverse legislations and dominations, except it be by subordination, as there is no place for two heads upon one body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 12.</head>
                  <p n="12">XII. The next assertion I am to make good that the Churches of the congregationall way are compatible with the Magistrates power in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering a Nationall Church way.</p>
                  <p>In order to this I believe it may be proved, 1. that in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of the Iewes there was both this Church way of Congregation, and yet the while a Nationall publick worship set up through all the Land by the Magistrates jurisdiction and direction. 2. That in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians time particular Churches were modelled according to the particular Churches of the Iewes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97969:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 13.</head>
                  <p>This congregationall Church-way is made out by the 23. chapter of Leviticus v. 1, 2 and 3. <hi>speak unto the children of Israel, &amp;c. six dayes shall work be done; but the seventh is the Sabbtah of rest, an holy convocation, ye shall doe no work therein: it is the Sabbath of the Lordin all your habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> where. 1. we have a convocation, and a holy one every Sabbath. 2. near every families dwelling place, at the distance, which is called in the Evangelists a Sabbath dayes journey: for, to travell a Sabbath day Iourney was to goe to the house of convocation, and to goe no further then the house of convocation was deemed the fulfilling of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Ezech. 16. v. 29. <hi>abide every man in his place, let no man goe out of his place on the seventh day,</hi> that is, let none goe any whither but to the place of convocation, for they could not keep the Sabbath without a holy convocation kept near every ones dwelling. Now that these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations cannot be meant of nationall and festivall meetings, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; for those were appointed but thrice in the year and far from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones dwelling place: after the building of the Temple, they were celebrated either before the Tabernacle, or in the outer Court of the Temple. Now had they been bound to repair to Ierusalem every Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, it would not have been a fulfilling of the command, not to stirr from the dwelling place. These convocations or synagogues were particular Churches assembled in a temple or house, who had severall names according to their severall uses, being called sometimes sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, sometimes schooles and houses of teaching, expounding, and houses of prayers: In these houses there was a more solemn meeting on the seventh day and every new moon, of all those that dwelt near by praying and hearing the expositions of the law of Moses. The work was carried on most by Doctors, Rabbies, Prophets and teachers of the law, and those that were most assiduous to hear them were called disciples, and sate at the Rabbies feet, asking questions and hearing their answers and resolutions, sometimes a new comer might interpose, as we see by the example of Iesus Christ, Luk. the fourth, and by the Apostles enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the synagogues. These disciples were called young Prophets and sons of the Prophets, and they were indifferently of all tribes and were different from those that by an extraordinary call were sent from God to whole Nations to deliver a speciall message, and foretell fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture things and denounce judgement; and one Esaias or Ezechiel
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97969:11"/>might supply the office and place of thousands, but the other Prophets were so called in the same sense that Iohn the Baptist was called a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, who never foretold future things: and Aaron was called the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of Moses, because he was his interpreter, Exod. 7. v. 4. The great number of these Prophets sheweth that their ordinary employment was to doe what the Ministers of the Gospell did, <hi>viz.</hi> to exhort, to teach, to comfort, to rebuke: they were in so great number that when Iezabel sought to destroy them all, Obadiah did hide one hundred of them in a cave, and as there were many of these Prophets and sons of the Prophets, so were they dispersed into many brother-hoods, fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, schools or synagogues; <hi>they have burnt up</hi> (saith the Psalmist 74. v. 8.) <hi>all the Synagogues of God in the Land,</hi> Calvin upon the place saith that people were every Sabbath day in synagogues to hear the reading and exposition delivered by the elder Prophets and to call upon God by prayer. In such sanctuaries and congregations David often saith, he will praise God and that God is gracious to his people.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 14.</head>
                  <p>These synagogues or convocations were particular churches of the nature of our congregationall churches in England, independent on any nationall Church or Commonwealth judicatory made up of Priests, Levites and elders of the people, meeting either in a Sanedrim of 70. persons or in those of 23. that judged the people at the gates: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides there could not be any consociation of all these convocations by their deputies to make up a nationall Church; for, then there would have been two nationall church judicatories coordinate, and collateral, and independant each on the other: and were there any such thing in Israel we should read of some orders and constitutions delivered by the nationall assembly of the Rabbies and Prophets unto each particular convocation: and it is further proved that these convocations did not depend on any generall judicatory or Sanedrim, by the practise of the faithfull people under Ieroboam and other idolatrous Kings; for, it was a capitall crime to appeal or repair about any matter to Ierusalem, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend at those solemn meetings enjoined by the law of Moses three times in the year, and every seventh year; and therefore to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from Idolatry they frequented as much as they could those places of convocations as appeareth by a notable example, 2. Kings 4. v. 22. for when the Shunamitish woman desired an asse to ride on to Elisha,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97969:12"/>her husband told her, <hi>wherefore will you goe to him this day, it is neither new Moon nor Sabbath.</hi> We doe not read that these convocations were invested with any jurisdiction, or that that the Rabbies or chief Prophets teaching in these convocation-houses, had any power of ruling or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning and of making lawes, which obliged those that were taught, and required submission to them for fear of any punishment or censure inflicted by them. I cannot better compare the extent, of the power of such Rabbies in the houses of convocation then to that of Zeno, Plato or Aristotle over their schollars who with willing submission embraced their sayings and precepts, so that the Prince or Doctor of the school needed not any restraining or coercive discipline to order them; and indeed it is very probable that the schools of the Greek Philosophers were modelled after the Iewish convocations or schools.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 15.</head>
                  <p>That besides these convocations set up in all the Land of Canaan, there was a publick nationall worship and forme of religion, ordered and commanded by the Prince, Iudges and Magistrates of the people and not by the Priests and Levites, much lesse by these Rabbies and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, we need no more proofs then we need a candle to see at noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; one worship was to continue to the end of the world, th'other was legall, typicall, ceremoniall, and was no longer to continue then the Leviticall worship, the Presthood, the Altar, the Temple and the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices were to hold. This kind of nationall Iewish Church-way was to give place to a Christian nationall Church-way; where there is no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther use of Priests, Levites, Altar, Sacrifice and ceremoniall law; and the Iewish congregationall way was to remain for the substance of it, under the oeconomie of the Gospell the very same, only this latter was to be performed under greater light and manifestations of truths and graces: in the former congregationall way Christ's Sacrifice on the Crosse was preached by the Sacrifice of a contrite and of a broken heart, and justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Faith in the Blood of Christ, was delivered by the non impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of sins, Psalme 32. In the latter way which is that of the Christian congregations and convocations, Christ his coming in the flesh, his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, resurrection, intercession and the benefits that accrue from them are lively, plainly and without figures set forth unto us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97969:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 16.</head>
                  <p>Yet there is that difference in those Churches wayes, both nationall and congregationall betwixt the constitution under the Old Testament and that under the New, that the nationall and congregationall way was under the Old Testament quite different in kind from the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall, but not so under the New, under which they differ nothing at all in the worship and the matter of it, nor in the Ministers that attend it, neither as I conceive, in the safety, but only in the manner of deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and attending it: for in the congregationall Christian way, men congregate willingly and voluntarily for the very love of the truth; and only for conscience sake without any outward consideration from men, but in the Christian nationall; all men doe not goe to the places of Gods worship only for the love of the truth and by a meer dictate of conscience, but also that they may appear in the eyes of the world to be conformable to the received and recommended nationall worship, or for fear of ill repute, or of being damnified in their private affairs. It were to be wished that all men and dwellers under one Magistrate were so willing to attend pure ordinances and were so holy in their lives, that they might be all one holy congregation to the Lord; so that there were no other Church-way besides the nationall; or that all men of the same Nation and territory were so minded to attend pure ordinances in a congregationall way that there were no need to set up a nationall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and a way of religion by a power of Magistracy: but neither of them being ever to be expected the soverain Magistrate in every Nation and territory ought not only to give way to all sorts of men that agree with him, in the fundamentall of Christian Religion to chuse both the person by whom they will be taught and such ordinances, fellowship or congregation, by which they expect to receive more edification and growth in grace, but besides he ought not only for the further edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of those that love best this congregational way, but specially &amp; chiefly for the instructing &amp; building up in Christ those that expect to be invited and would have ordinances made ready to their hands, to set up by law publick ordinances, appoint places of meeting, Ministers, revenues, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, schools and all waies, whereby learning, piety, purity of worship may universally and publickly be contenanced and ordered; for were there no other Church-way under an orthodox Magistrate but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall, it would be a way to bring an extire extinction of all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97969:13"/>and fear of God in all those that would not congregate willingly, or may be could not for want of the sincerity of membership required in all them that congregate; so that in a short time, the greatest part of the Nation would be lawlesse, because void of religion and the care of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 17.</head>
                  <p>But however the Magistrate countenance ordinances, and in what way soever; the meeting of men in one place under the same Ministery and ordinances, whether it be of members of the same place and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood or no, is the true adequate proper definition and description of a true visible Church in a Scripture sence; and such a Church, partly by a Divine positive right as it is a congregation of Christians, partly by a Divine naturall civill politick right, as it is a society of men endowed with prudence, wisdome; liberty of mind and body, hath power and right to govern it self and make orders most convenient for their own subsistence: all other acceptions of Churches are but improperly made use of: for a nationall Church is the same with the Christian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and this association of Churches is meerly of humane prudence and not of Christs Institution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 18.</head>
                  <p>But how private Churches came to varie from their first institution by assuming some thing like a jurisdiction both in the Iewish State, and since Christian Religion was professed, it will not be amisse to declare 1. I take for granted that the first Christian Churches were like those con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations or synagogues frequented every Sabbath-day in the Iewish Commonwealth, and like those of the brethren of the congregational way independent on any other Church, Synode or Church judicatory; for so the Centuriators tell us, cent. 2. cap. 7. and Vignier, whom the most pious Prelat and learned Dr. Usher took for the faithfullest writer that ever wrote the Church-History, <hi>the form of Government in this age was almost democraticall, for every Church had equall power to teach the Word of God, to administer the Sacraments, to absolve and excommunicate hereticks and those that led a dissolute life, to elect, to call or to ordain Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, to depose them when occasion required to erect schools, to call Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, to ask the opinions of others upon doubts or controversies.</hi> 2. We doe not read that those convocations or synagogues in Levitic. 23. afore the people was led into captivity were invested with any jurisdiction,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97969:13"/>but only lived in a brotherly confederacy each member preferring ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love and mutuall condescension; besides, they had no need of discipline, since all the people in those convocations were as so many scholars attending and hearkning to the lectures and expositions of a Professour, Doctor or Preacher, and had no occasion to confer about lawes of their government, no more then the auditory and the whole congregation when they meet upon a Sunday in a Temple to hear the Minister: 3. when the people were led into captivity and their own Magistrates were removed which kept up the publick Nationall Church-way, those convocations &amp; houses of prayer by degrees &amp; lapse of time changed nature and became as many little Commonwealths en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with jurisdiction, not only performing exercises, as we see Act. 13. v. 27. and chap 15. v. 21. but also having coercive lawes &amp; Iudges, handling all caufes and matters as well Ecclesiasticall (as they call them) as civill: and whereas afore the captivity none but Rabbies and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets taught, afterwards Priests and Levites and the Elders of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were joined to them in one synagogue; and so putting out of the synagogue, which was a judiciall sentence of the assembly, and which some are pleased to call excommunication, came in fashion; for afore the captivity there is no footstep of excommunication: thus synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues were invested not only with a faculty to perform duties and acts of worship to God, but also with a power of Magistracy. 4. These sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues being turned or converted into Christian Churches, retained the same construction and qualification in performing church duties, and exercising power of Magistracy; which for 300. years after Christ was assumed by the consent of members and afterwards was delegated by the Emperours. This way of Magistracy, it seems, was approved of by St. Paul, 1. Cor. 6. v. 1, 2, 3. &amp;c. where it is evident that St. Paul recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends there should be in the Church, besides those that labour in the word and doctrine, some of lesse eminency amongst them to decide differences and controversies of another nature, albeit some think they were set by St. Paul only as arbitrators, and not as Magistrates of the same power as the elders in the synagogues. Reverend Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> hath these words about the meaning of that place, <hi>afterwards to take the Corinthians off from going to infidel Iudges, he requireth them to decide the matter themselves, till the time come that the Saints shall judge the world; that is, till the time come that there shall be a Christian Magistracy.</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97969:14"/>Those that decided such matters were called Elders, <hi>seniores,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till the Emperors became Christian, who instead of them erected audiences of Bishops, to which it was free to repair, or to a secular judge; which custome <hi>Ambrose</hi> did not like so well, when as St. Paul would have matters worth complaint to be composed by the elders of the Church, and wisheth that the Elders in use in the synagogue, and afterwards in the Christian primitive Church, were again erected and appointed in Churches.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 19.</head>
                  <p>Hereto the Churches power assumed by common consent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, changed hands, and was taken up by the Magistrate and dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated to him again: and yet however the Emperours were affected, either for, or against Arius, good men used every where to meet in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular conclaves, meetings, and fellowships, and houses of prayer to confer about heavenly things, and to humble themselves and pray to God for the removing of those evils and judgements, which bad Bishops and Emperours did strive to bring upon the true Churches of Christ: and the Emperour kept that jurisdiction in the settling a natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church-way, discipline, and religion, untill the Bishops of Rome snatched it from them; and enjoyed it many centuries of years, till the reformation begun by Luther in many Nations, namely in England, where that same jurisdiction in ordering matters of religion, in a natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall way was reunited again to the Magistrate of the countrey, as many of our Acts of Parliament tell us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 20.</head>
                  <p>To bring the matter to some head: as we have seen that the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall way is very compatible with the Magistrates jurisdiction in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering matters of religion in a publick way, so no doubt it is altogether incompatible and inconsistent with an Ecclesiasticall Synodical juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, if they make it independent on the Magistrate; for, 1. That Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical national jurisdiction must comprehend all men in the same territory, and consequently all the men of the congregational Churches: for it is no jurisdiction, if it be free for any man to withdraw from it, and adhere to the congregational way. 2. most men that are not well informed about the extent of power wherewith synods are invested, will be continually fleeting about the measure of their subjection to them, when one party maintaineth that Synods have a judicial power
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97969:14"/>authoritatively to determine, and to impose lawes and ordinances, upon private churches, and th' other holds that Synods have but a faculty to advise and give counsell. 3. and since there is hardly a man of the congregational way, but is willing to be partaker of some of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances (yea may be of all) administred by that Minister who is for a national Ecclesiastical jurisdiction, and yet is not willing to submit to his jurisdiction, you shall have a member of a church that hath not submitted to the jurisdiction of that Church. 4. the nature of the Church in Scripture sence will sooner admit a jurisdiction included within a particular Church, than within a Presbyterian Church inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on the Magistrate. 1. because such a Presbyterian national Church is no Church in Scripture sence, and therefore no jurisdiction can be ascribed to it. 2. the holy writ mentions but three kinds of Churches, that of the elect, the Catholick visible Church, &amp; the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church; there is no room for an English, Gallican, or Dutch Church in a Scripture sence, and so no jurisdiction belongeth to such a Church; for if the Catholick church that hath a reall being in the world and in the Scripture, cannot by any means be invested with jurisdiction, much lesse a national church, which hath no existence but in the abuse by the vulgar, who call all the private churches of one nation by the word <hi>Church.</hi> Many other incompatibilities I omit for brevity sake; and which will never fall out, when the Magistrate takes in hand all national church jurisdiction, how few or many soever churches there be of the congregational way whose jurisdiction is of no great extent, and of no dangerous consequence, no more then the jurisdiction of a father of a family, who needs not the inspection and direction of the Magistrate to govern his family with such religious orders as he thinks best; whereas it would bring a great conflict into the State if so many families as there be private churches in one territory had the libertie to associate in one entire body, and take up and exercise a jurisdiction, which should be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent on the jurisdiction of the Soverain Magistrate: this is the case of a nationall Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction independent on that of the Soverain Magistrate, and which hath caused strange conflicts in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinat, Scotland, Geneva and other places, whereof I have brought many examples elsewhere, no such inconvenience can befall, even by admitting that congregationall churches were endued with a jurisdiction independent on the Magistrates jurisdiction; for the juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97969:15"/>of many little churches of equall authority not combined, will never breed any faction to the disturbing of the publick peace, yet the keeping of them a sunder from joyning heads and counsels, availes much for the strengthening of his soverainty, according to the saying, <hi>divide &amp; Impera.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPT. II. <hi>Of Tithes and setled maintenance for the Ministry.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>MAny of late who have written of this subject have spent much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ink in vain, without stating the right of Tithes: some are very eager to prove that they are of Divine perpetuall right, and not alterable without sin by any law of man: others, that they are of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right, but to be of no longer standing than the Mosaicall lawes and ceremonies, and so to be abrogated by a Christian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate: some disprove wholly the use of them, not because they are tythes, but because they are setled maintenance for the Ministry; which maintenance they would wholly take away in order (it seems) to the abolishing of a standing Ministery imployed by the Soverain Magistrate for promoting the settlement of religion and piety in a nationall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick way. They are in the right, in my judgement, that hold they are to be retained, 1. by Divine right, so far as by Divine right the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strat who must order matters of religion in a nationall publick way, is to make a provision for the Ministery, and that no provision is more just e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall and reasonable than that of Tythes. 2. by humane right, because the Magistrates Godly prudence hath thought this way most just and equall, yet by a right that is alterable if the Magistrate can find a better way to set up publick maintenance of the Ministry. I am sure <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wolph,</hi> who brought the Saxon-Heptarchy into a Monarchy, conferred the Tythes of all the Kingdome upon the Church by a charter <hi>anno</hi> 855. which was never yet repealed: and so far Tythes are of humane right in England.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>Those that hold them be of perpetuall right, have committed many
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97969:15"/>grosse mistakes. 1. the Divine right of the law of Tythes is not in the number of 10. but in the proportion of one to ten, which God allowed as a reasonable maintenance for a tenth part of the people, even all the tribe of Levi, and to defray all the charges about the Levitical worship: now the tribe of Levi was about the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg> part, if we take in those that were not of the tribe of Levi, and were attending on many low employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments necessarily to be discharged about the Levites or the Levitical service, and were to live of the leavings of the children of Levi. Now this proportion of one to ten being of Divine institution and right, this law of Tythes cannot be fulfilled in a Christian Commonwealth, except the Ministry be so numerous as to make the tenth part of the people, or unless their maintenance be of that proportion, as one is to the number of ten, which would be altogether unreasonable &amp; unjust; for then one Minister who usually maketh not the two hundredth man might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grosse in a little time the estates of 200. men. Since then the Ministers of the Gospell were to be either by Gods providence, permission or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, nothing so numerous as the proportion of one is to ten, is it probable that the law enjoyning an Israelite to pay one of ten can stand in force under the Gospel, and be fulfilled when 500. Parishioners pay the tenth part of their yearly revenue in corn, fruits and money to one Minister? had it been so, then one Levite had been verypoorly shared in comparison of one Minister of the Gospell: for the Levite could receive but of one man the tenth, th' other (it may be) the tenth of 500. or one thousand: and whereas the Levite could receive but 1. in 10. yearly, the five hundred parishioners worth it may be 10. l. a year a man one with another would afford 500. l. of yearly mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to their single Minister: but sure God meant more than one of ten to the tribe of Levi, and not so much to the Ministers of the Gospel, and the number 10. stands for a Levitical maintenance as the 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. pigg is called Tythe though it be not the tenth. <hi>Chrysostome Sermon.</hi> 103. mentioneth a farr greater proportion as <hi>fruits, first fruits, tenths, tenths again, thirteens, sicles, half sicles, meat-offerings, heave-offerings, their therumah of the tenth of all, that is, the hundredth part,</hi> besides their free entertaining of Levites in their houses; there being hardly a good house where there was not a Levite. And as God never meant the tenth to the Ministers, so was it never given, if the Tythes be taken in the lump or if it be taken notice that a great part of the Tythes are impropriate &amp; that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97969:16"/>much land, many fruits, cole-pits, mines, a world of wares and dwelling-houses are not tythable. But the Tythes paid to the Minister are impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called tenths; for were the duly paid, they would amount to the fifth or sixth part of every landed man in corn, grasse, fruit and cattle. Suppose one countrey Parish had one 1000. Akers of Land tillage and pasture worth one with another 20. s. an Aker, I conceive if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishioners of one consent should give to their Minister in lieu of Tythes 100. Akers of ground to till and manure himself, or to let to another, that then those Tythes should be exactly the tenth of the revenue of the whole Parish, <hi>viz.</hi> a 1000. l. for a 1000. Akers of land: but the said 100. Akers of ground being tilled and manured at the charge of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, no doubt but the Parish, besides the 100. Akers of ground (which being let will afford 100. l. yearly) giveth another 100. l. to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, which he saves in countrey manage, and in keeping of servants Teams and ploughs, and so his Tythes are no more tenths but fifths.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§. 3.</head>
                  <p>The law of Tythes cannot be of a perpetuall Divine right, in regard this revenue allowed for the upholding a ceremoniall worship, and for maintenance of a Leviticall Priesthood, was to cease with the Priest and Priesthood, which ended at the same time that Iesus Christ said <hi>all is fulfilled.</hi> When there was no more need of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, good reason that gifts should be no longer brought to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, those also that served at the Altar being dismissed, as of no further use. 2. For this reason the Ministers of the Gospell are not to challenge the continuance of Tythes, in regard they did not succeed to the Priests and Levites but to the Prophets that taught in schools, and which we read not to have been maintained out of the Leviticall Tythes. 3. the lawes which God gave to the Iewes were fitted to their Commonwealth only, and were not intended to oblige Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians to the observation of them, as all ceremoniall, and many politicks laws; as for example, the law about trying Virgins, and that law which gives a double portion to the elder, which latter law was so far from being a precept binding the Christians, that it hath not been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for an example to be imitated in divers very orderly Christian Commonwealths, as this of England, who thinks it no sin if a man dye without a will, that all his Land should go to the elder son: what war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant have we from Scripture, that the law of Tythes carries with it a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97969:16"/>greater necessity of duty, so as not to vary from it? Lastly, as the <hi>jus Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> of Tythes was to hold no longer then Priests and Levites, so was it to be of no longer standing then those men that attended the publick nationall worship, had no other maintenance then that of Tythes, for they had no inheritance among their brethren: but the Ministers of the Gospell being neither Priests nor Levites, and their Ministry being quite of another nature, and having an inheritance among their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which they bequeath to their children, that Divine institution of Tythes must needs cease, when their persons and their Ministery for which Tythes were instituted were taken away.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§. 4.</head>
                  <p>Others being carried to extremes, say that the law of Tythes was ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, and consequently is abrogated. To this I say. 1. We are freed from paying Tythes to Priests and Levites, because freed from Priests and Levites; but we are not obliged not to set up Tythes by an humane constitution, or not to bestow them upon the Ministers of the Gospell; we are freed from bringing a gift to the Altar, but we are not hindered by that freedome from bringing a gift to the Altar, nor to bring a gift to the poor of the Church. 2. we are freed from that bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to place more holinesse in the number of ten than in that of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Christians doe not conceive there is more sin in the Minister to accept the worth of 100. l. in corne or in grasse for his salary, than to have it in mony out of the publick treasury. And if it be free for a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord to let his Land to a tenant for such a sum of mony payable yearly, sure he hath the liberty to contract with him for the value of it in sheafes or in quarters of corne as they can agree; and why not as well for 10. sheaffes as for 20? 3. Tythes are put among <hi>res medias,</hi> as eating and not eating, which have no sanctity or sin in themselves, but as they are used, good, if directed to a good end, bad, if they be misused. That law were sinfull that should recall again the distinction of meats, the use of candlesticks, snuffers, vessels and the like, for that typical end for which they were then commanded by God, but that law would not be amisse now that should forbid the killing of young cattle in the spring for their encrease, and set up candlesticks to bear candles to give light in the Church when the Sun is down.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§. 5.</head>
                  <p>As for those that will abolish Tythes, because they would not have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97969:17"/>any settled maintenance for Ministers, my soul and reason doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into their counsell: they are no almes; they are <hi>debitum Iustitiae non charitatis.</hi> It is a very equall and just maintenance that falls and rises as years are cheap or dear, and as Lands improve, so Tythes do: in dear years, when lesse corn, no lesse mony is accrewing than when there is plenty of corn. This advantage stipends doe want; for being the same everie year, they may prove a short allowance in a dear year and in a short time. Tythes are the free gift of the earth and not a benevolence or gratuity of the people, for they have no right or property in them: they never bought nor paid for them, neither could they come by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, for, that which was not their forefathers could not descend to them: Neither came Tythes to the people by donation, which they can never shew: the people meerly afford their labour in exchange of the labour in word and doctrine dispensed to them and yet scarce that, since it is due when the Tythes are impropriate, so that both la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Tythes are like a rent that the Land is charged with, not by the Landlord, but by the state and law of the Land, without any da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage losse or diminution of rent or profits to the owner, who bought the Land upon that consideration that it was Tythable, and which had been the dearer had it been infeodated at the first purchase. Neither doth the State give now any thing of its own but protection, interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing its authority that the gift of God and of the former Kings through the labour of the people be not hindred. If any revenue is arbitrary, it is the gift of Tythes, for it is <hi>ad arbitrium Dei non hominis,</hi> for as God giveth raine when he pleaseth, and more or lesse of it, so doth he give an answerable harvest.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP.T. III. <hi>Of Ministers capacity to sit and vote in Parliament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Am of this opinion that the very refined mistery of iniquity whereof St. Paul speaketh, 2. Thessal. 2. is the earthly dominion called exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion above all that is called God, which the Bishops of Rome have as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed over the Kings and Nations of the earth, under the pretence of an Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction distinct and independent on the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97969:17"/>jurisdiction, and that the main weapon in the Popes hand to get himself this dominion hath been this fabulous thunder (and not so much as a flash) of excommunication, so that nothing hath more contributed towards the advancing of this mystery then the opinion of two jurisdictions in every state collateral and coordinate, whereof the Magistrate hath the managing and keeping of the one, and the clergy, and in chief the Pope, the keeping of the other: that church-men are Governors of the Church, and the Magistrates, Rulers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; that the Magistrates in their civil assemblies must judge and order civil affairs; but that in Synodes the Ministers of the Gospell must sit, vote and order matters of Religion. The Pope and his clergy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gained thus far, and perswaded men that there be two jurisdictions, have in consequence obtained easily to subject and subordinate the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil jurisdiciton to the Ecclesiasticall, and subdue unto himself the Kings and Nations of the earth: for <hi>Baronius, Bellarmin,</hi> &amp;c. after they have very rationally demonstrated the incompatibility of two jurisdictions coordinate and collateral in one and the same territory, &amp; the necessity of subordinating one jurisdiction to the other, have concluded as ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally that the civil jurisdiction ought rather to be subordinate to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall then the Ecelesiasticall to the civil, whereas if the truth were well known that this double jurisdiction Ecclesiasticall and civil, is a meer mockerie and sathans devising to bring at length the Magistrats jurisdiction under his bow: and were it well known that the Ministers of the Gospell have no jurisdiction, but that of the word over mens hearts and consciences, the Popes Kingdome would soon fall to the ground, there would not be two governments in every territory, one of the Church and th' other of the Commonwealth: there would be but one Christian Commonwealth, one power, one supreme counsell, judging of and ordering all matters, whereby men are to live soberly, righteously and Godly in this present world, looking for that blessed hope, &amp;c. no member of that Commonwealth what ever profession he be of, that loves peace, religion, that hath wisedome and prudence, that is concerned as a citizen, husband, Landlord to contribute towards the settlement of the Commonwealth should be kept off from sitting and voting in publick assemblies, by what title soever called or distinguished; and Ministers of the Gospell should as well sit and vote in Parliament as other men are admitted to vote and sit in Synodes: for I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97969:18"/>that it is a wrong both to religion and the peaceable and Godly settlement of a Commonwealth, that Ministers doe not sit and vote in Parliament, and are not admitted equally with all other ranks of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: to make that good, I further propound these considerations fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§. 1.</head>
                  <p>The keeping of Ministers from sitting in Parliament hath given to the Ministers just ground to have judicatories of their own, where the laity should not be admitted, and this hath occasioned the rooting in mens minds the opinion of a double jurisdiction, wherein Ministers find themselves much loosers; for besides that, thereby they loose quite their share in the Magistrates jurisdiction, whereof all ranks of men are made partakers, it falls out, that while they challenge unto themselves entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction, they enjoy but the bare name of it, since it necessarily returns into the possession of the Magistrate and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be exercised without him. May be the clergy and Ministers must thank themselves that they are not admitted with men of all profession to have a share in governing the Commonwealth, having begun to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude themselves by challenging a jurisdiction of their own, indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on the Magistrate, and thereby given just grounds to be quite cashiered and got nothing but an empty thing, a cloud and a shadow which they have clasped in lieu of a substance: and the Magistrate in the reformation made no haste to restore unto them their rights, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade them from parting with an Ecclesiasticall jurisdiction, which at the best was but a sword which they held by the blade, though the hilt be the hand of the Magistrate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§. 2.</head>
                  <p>There being in a Parliament men of all sorts and ranks, Gentlemen, Lawyers, Physitians driving the same interest to promote religion, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; lawes, it is altogether unreasonable that Ministers equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned should be, as it were culled out of the number, and much more that Ministers should be like the Gibeonites, who must be subject to the law they never had a hand in.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§. 3.</head>
                  <p>It is known that men though chosen for their wisdome and faithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, yet doe not sit and vote in Parliaments, Synods, &amp;c. as they are artists, or invested with a profession and endued with knowledge or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97969:18"/>science, but as they are invested with judicial authority delegated or as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed by consent; sure a Physitian in a Parliament may discourse of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick in the Parliament as Physitian, but he doth no more give his assent to a law for regulating Apothecaries as Physitian, than either a Merchant or a Draper give their vote to a law <hi>quatenus</hi> Merchant or Draper. So then Ministers being to sit in Parliament are not to sit as a distinct order as Ministers, and as Bishops did sometime challenge, nor give their suffrage to a bill for reforming or regulating religion as Ministers of the Gospel. But Ministers are to sit and vote in the capacity that Bishops did sit, when they voted as Barons and Peeres of the realme, and not as Bishops, and in that capacity that Lawyers or Physitians have in the same Parliament: for even Ministers in a Synode, though they discourse per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently of Divinity as Ministers; yet they do not, and they ought not to give their vote to a Canon against heresie or blasphemie as Ministers, but as Iudges and men invested with judiciall authority.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§. 4.</head>
                  <p>It seems to me unreasonable and unconscionable that men never so wise, Godly and experienced should be barred off from those assemblies and be made incapable to afford their wit and counsell, because of their habit and profession, as if a man refused to take a wholesome remedy from a Lawyer: were Ministry not sutable with the employment of a Parliament man, yet as none would refuse the reaping of a benefit, what ever hand should give it, so none ought to refuse a wholesome counsell, because given by a Minister; and how can it be better imparted then in a publick State Assembly? did a Minister know a secret to blow up all the King of Spaine ships in their havens, his Ministry should not hinder the State to make use of such a man: but of all professions, Ministry is most agreable to the making of lawes grounded upon Iustice, equity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science as all must be, and their parts lye that way more then those of Physitians or Merchants.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§. 5.</head>
                  <p>Since the greatest end of Magistracy is to advance the Kingdom of the Lord Iesus, &amp; that for the obtaining of that end, it is needful to make lawes, and constitutions subservient to it, why should Ministers of all men be left out, whose education and profession renders them more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to advise for the obtaining of that great end?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97969:19"/>
                  <head>§. 6.</head>
                  <p>But the complication of the affairs that regulate religion in a national publick way, with those that regulate the Commonwealth is so great; yea there is so much affinity between all kinds of affairs and so much of religion in every constitution made by man, that of all men Ministers should be called on to advise as being most skilld and studied in the judgement of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§. 7.</head>
                  <p>There is the same reason for Ministers to sit in Parliament, as there was for Priests, Levites and Prophets to sit in synagogues and judicial assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Iewes; it being certain, that the great Sanedrim was a mixture of Priests and Levites, with the Princes and heads of the people. <hi>Iose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> tells us in the 2. Book against <hi>Appion</hi> that that Moses appointed Priests to be overseers and Iudges of all controversies and to condemn and punish.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>§. 8.</head>
                  <p>There is equall reason that if the supreme Magistrate calls lay men to sit and vote in Synodes, he should call the clergy to sit and vote in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; for none of them vote in Parliament or Synod as Ministers, Lawyers, Physitians, Merchants, but as members of the Commonwealth, and invested by those that sent them with judicial authority.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>§. 9.</head>
                  <p>There was no such thing so much as heard of for many hundred years that Ministers and Bishops should be thought incapable to sit and vote in the supreme Court of the Nation. In England, France, Germany, &amp;c. though the Pope had already much advanced the hatching of his two eggs Ecclesiastical and civil jurisdiction, for 5. or 600. years the State as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies were a mixture of Senators, Bishops, Abbots, Lords, Gentlemen, &amp;c. and in these assemblies all matters were debated and handled; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we had lately some footstep in England, when Bishops sate in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and even in the Popish Nations, as in France there is no high Court of Iudicature without some of the Clergy in it; only they usually goe aside when some criminal cause is handled, but not when an edict about criminal causes is debated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>§. 10.</head>
                  <p>And here we must distinguish the power of legislation from that of jurisdiction; for the profession of Ministry doth not render the Ministers
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97969:19"/>uncapable to make lawes even about crimes, treasons and the like; but it may well render them not so fit in a Court of Iudicature to sit upon life and death, or to exercise any part of jurisdiction, as of Iustices of peace, Majors or of Iudges, but to use a homely comparison they are fit to make a coach but not to drive it, and to be coachmen: a Physitian can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be blamed to accept to be chosen burgesse for Parliament by his Countrey, but the office of a Sheriff or Major or Sergeant will not so well suit with his profession of practitioner of Physick, the like may we say of a Minister of the Gospel: and besides many Ministers parts lye not so much for preaching as for Government, as St. Paul tells us 1. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. ch. 5. and such may be the fitter members of Parliament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>§. 11.</head>
                  <p>And if religion; church-discipline, maintenance for Ministers by Tythes, or otherwise, taking and giving use and increase of mony, must be established by law; &amp; by law Idolatry, prophaness, perjury, taking Gods name in vain must be banished, it seems to me an unreasonable thing that Ministers should have no hand in making that law, who of all men are entrusted to know and to declare Gods mind and counsell, the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and conscionablenesse of the law, and who besides are invested with titles and office of Governors, Rulers and Overseers of Churches, and of Ambassadors from Christ: And albeit Ministers have no jurisdiction at all, but that which they exercise in their Ministry over the spirits, hearts and consciences of men, yet, as they are not by their Ministerial function deprived of a Paternal, marital or Heril power and jurisdiction, when Gods providence doth call them to it, so neither doth their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterial sacred function diminish any thing of a capacity to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred with that jurisdiction, which mainly is conversant about order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duties or actions to be performed by those who are setled in that function.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>§. 12.</head>
                  <p>Since the Godlinesse of these times hath abolished the distinction of Church and State, of civil and Ecclesiastical jurisdiction, and taken away the distinction of clergy and laity, so far as to conceive that the laity is none of the Lords inheritance, or to constitute two orders in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in order to introduce two collateral jurisdictions: And since now God hath in these dayes powred of the spirit of the Prophets upon the multitude, and is a working to make of them, both one holy City
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97969:20"/>and one Commonwealth to the Lord: since those times of ignorance are past, when the clergy had all the sway and knowledge on their side, so far as to make a great wonder to see a lay man that could read, and they would say, <hi>legit ut Clericus,</hi> and for that a man deserved pardon of the Prince, since the walls of partition of gifts and parts are removed and not fastned particularly more to the Ministers of the Gospel then to the people or Magistrate, since Ministers want no insight in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Commonwealth: since (I say) these things be so, I cannot see the lesse shadow of reason why Ministers, who have the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest by birth, are alike citizens and members of that Commonwealth and have a religion lands, peace, liberty to secure to themselves and to their posterity, shall not be alike made capable to sit and vote in the Parliament of that Commonwealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>§. 13.</head>
                  <p>It is the law of nature and of Nations, that those that have power to depute and delegate are supposed to have a capacity to be deputed and delegated: now it is known that Ministers in England do actually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise that power to depute and delegate members to the Parliament; particularly in the choice of members for the University, is there any thing more reasonable then that the principal members of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities, as are the heads of Colledges and Halls be chosen, whether Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters or others, and that those that are Ministers be not by their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry rendered more incapable to be members of Parliament, than others in regard of Physick or civil law, which they professe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97969:20"/>
            <head>An entrance into this one Proposal towards the settling of a lasting and flourishing Commonwealth, Which is <hi>That Parents inheritances be divided equally among their children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe <hi>Printer</hi> having desired of me to make this Book either shorter or longer by one page, this subject came into my mind; whereof I have among my papers at <hi>Oxford</hi> a discourse in writing. The drift of it is to shew, that the grand <hi>arcanum Imperii</hi> to preserve Democracy and keep it from going back to Monarchy, is to make a law for sharing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances, into more equal portions among children. This proposal, as I remember, I make good by many arguments out of Scripture, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the authority of the civil law, and the civilians, and the practise of all States, that meant to procure liberty, peace and plenty to the people. The holy Scripture never allowed but a double portion to the elder. I alledge the examples of the Romans, and of the nations, at the dissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Roman Empire; namely that of the Gaules, where their Princes divided the Kingdom among many children: by which they receded as much from those wayes that strengthen Monarchy, as by them they advanced the popular interest. I descend unto reasons, some of which I remember were, 1. This <hi>arcanum Democraticum</hi> is a mean to improve every parcel of ground, to enclose waste lands, to fill up the country with people, buildings and good husbandry, when younger brothers are kept at home having a little estate to manage, from an idle wandring life and from following wicked courses. I bring the example of those countreys, where brothers being shared alike, the land is much more improved, is fuller of people, lesse given to vanity, than where an elder carries all the estate and land, much consisting in parks, chases, wild forrests, instruments of vanity and idleness. 2. as sharing equally, children will reduce mens conditions into that condition, which is more agreable with Democracy, which is mainly upheld by an equality of ranks &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and where Magistracy, and not personal honour puts a difference
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97969:21"/>among men, so that disproportion, which gives all to the elder, begets a vast disproportion between men in their honours, ranks and fortunes, which in a short time will eat up the Commonwealth. 3. I presse this reason, that great houses and families, being continued in their high titles of honour and port, will be continually making towards Monarchical Government, from which they are perswaded, that their lustre and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is derived, and having fortunes answerable to their titles of honour, they will be more scorning and hating popularity, as endeavouring to pluck them down; and they themselves will be the more endeavouring to keep their distances, the more conscious they are that popularity and Magistracy as it is seen in Switzerland, are not compatible with No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. 4. but the principal reason and which ariseth from the very being and essential constitution of a Commonwealth, as it is so lately fetcht out of the bowels of Monarchy, is that in a short time, younger brothers, who exceed far the number of the elder, will join their interest with that of the Commonwealth, so that the State will need no other Army, but that of younger Brothers.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>